he was saying earlier in terms of
sensuality she said time to huge just quote you
she said time to huge just quote you
guys the only reason why one gives in to
sensuality it's because it's because one
doesn't want
what what I meant was that so
universally literally to every human
mind regardless of the culture education
religion practice whether they heard
about Buddhism or not it doesn't matter
it doesn't matter when a desire arises
in regard to anything obtainable to the
senses when that desire arises that
desire is is oppressing that's person
desire is that that sort of lack
pressure and need thirst hunger whatever
means it makes you act it pressures you
I mean you don't have to act that's the
whole point there's a human being a
choice but when desire arises the
automatic response is to give in to that
pressure of the desire and why would you
be giving in to the pressure of any
desire is because it's unpleasant
if the pressure of the desire is neutral
or Pleasant you wouldn't then spend all
the efforts and time gaining but your
desire bonds cuz you already be released
but that that desire it's already
unpleasant so in order for you to deal
with that displeasure you just give in
to whatever the desire promises so
that's what I mean by engaging
sensuality you do so to be free from the
central pressure of the desire so when
people say no I enjoy my senses that's
that's that's a mistake that they
themself believe it if they were to stop
and think about and see when there is a
non satisfied or unsatisfied desire is
that Pleasant is that what you want it
isn't you enjoy sensuality for as long
as you think and hold the view that you
can access things that your senses want
you but sooner or later time will come
when you won't be able to fulfill your
desires and then again you don't just
think all these particular desires I
can't fault fulfill I mean some people
might think that but the point is to see
then the nature of the desire in the
first place even the ones you can
fulfill so to speak as in give in to
their pressure and seek the object of
their desire until you feel fed up with
it and even feel like my desire
disappears so in other words you can
never fulfill the desire the point of
desire is to stare this
exactly it requires a non satisfaction
for it to be so that's why if you stop
and think about you realize the only the
only reason you are engaged with
sensuality people would be engage with
sensuality is because the the pressure
of the desire is unpleasant and they
don't know any other escape and that's
that's the whole point
and that's an insane like then whenever
you encounter any other form of this
pleasure your only way of dealing it is
sensuality which is our people turn to
food music sexual intercourse or
whatever else when they're sort of
feeling down or depressed or something's
bothering them they just commit harder
because that's the only form that they
they can resemble a relief of relieving
oneself of that pressure but actually
you're just making it worse because the
more you are dependent on running away
of this from the desire the more
pressure that desire will exercise over
well first I mean you don't have to do
anything in a way but then you just
remain if you start seeing that Envy
sustained your own sensual your own
desires is something that's controlling
you the u.s. enslaved by then you have
to start seeing in the nature of before
you give in to the desire how it feels
to just have the desire and then you it
becomes like obviously clear as a day
that it's very unpleasant like even
sometimes when you can satisfy your
desires but maybe not quickly enough
that's some unpleasant either way that
discrepancy of desire is root
in disagreeable feel that pressure it's
very unpleasant so if you want to free
yourself from it you have to first start
restraining and making it worse through
giving in to that pressure of desire
it's raised like oh you're training
yourself to be stronger than something
else but in order to start doing that
you need to start assisting that thing
you're trying to be strong in regard so
if you just habitually giving in to the
desire and at the same time expected to
somehow be magically free from the
pressure of the desire but that just a
contradiction in terms
so the restraint needs to come first but
the one who wants to be free from desire
restraint needs to come first then the
obvious painful nature of the desire in
itself becomes apparent and I said that
before maybe another audio talks in life
and that's that's like initially when
people start restraining that pain that
arises from the desire they will think
it's because of my restraint but it
isn't restraint cannot cause you pain it
can only reveal the underlying pain of
the desire and not getting what the
desire wants and the similar of the of
the five animals like pulling you in
every the Buddha gave in like I knows
pulling you their own domains to to feed
in their own respective feeding grounds
every animal wants to go and eat as much
as it likes so I just want to go and
look at the pleasurable sites and avoid
this pleasure and same goes for every
sense so you can imagine that your
experience is how your existence is
basically you'd you tie to these five
animals you're inseparable from and
they're always overpowering you and
you're you're enabling them enabling
them even further when you're carelessly
just giving in to whatever desire your
eye wants to have or your ears or your
sense of touch so you can imagine if you
tie to five powerful animals and they
start running towards their respective
goals objects of their desire
you just run with it to avoid that
terribly painful pull that you will
experience if you start if you try
standing your ground but the animals are
stronger than you they will yank you in
it'll be very unpleasant but that
doesn't mean that that pain is not there
if you run with them
because that enables them to pull you
even harder so initially you have to
accept that sharp pain of restraint
which eventually you can see that it's
actually it's not the restraint the
stranger shows me what happens when
these animals yank in their respective
domains and I don't give in because if
the animals wouldn't be yanking they
wouldn't be any pain revealed by the
restraint imagine the animals are tamed
income and they just walk slowly and you
can just remain seated and not have to
run with them so they don't rip your arm
off but initially people get confused
and then this might start doing the
restraint but then all the pain that
arises as a result of being yanked by
these five senses they think it's
because they're saying no they think
it's because of the restraint and then
eventually they do they give back in but
it's not that pain is the nature of
being pressured by the senses by the
sense desire it's just when you run
along with it you kind of minimize the
pole so you pretend it's not there but
the fact is all you have to do is say no
to the desire and you see whether it's
still there or not that pain unless you
completely free of course so that's
something every anybody could benefit
from just learning how to say no to
themselves gradually more and in regard
to this in regard to unnecessary things
in regard to unnecessary luxuries in
regard to unnecessary indulgences
because you are each time you give in
carelessly like that the animals get
more to feed on which means they get
more powerful which means each time they
pull you you be less and less able to
resist those desires and very often and
I'm pretty sure many people can relate
to that out of their experience your own
desires takes you to the places you
don't want to be you know you like you
know you regret it even beforehand yet
you can't help it and you just drag
there and let alone when the old age
sets in or sickness when your senses
start to fail yet your mind is fully
dependent on that pleasure that you get
from that remote satisfaction of your
desires then the only source will I said
before the only kind of remotely resemblance
the only kind of remotely resemblance
way of relief from any disagreeable
feelings is taken away now consensus
can't enjoy anymore then you know eyes
can't can barely see it's painful to
listen it's hard to chew all the does
elicits not young doesn't have that much
energy yet your mind was dependent on
the constant run and now that's just
taken away so when the unpleasant
feelings arise and the world inevitably
now you have even less ground that's
where people are terrified of solitude
exactly yeah